Guide to the Samuel Bourne photographs, circa 1861-circa 1889 RL.00130
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Photographic prints, circa 1861-circa 1889; 1; 546 prints 21 boxes
  - Ghoom Bazaar. Darjeeling RY [Railway], circa 1880; 8 3/4 11 1/8 inches (Box 20, Print RL-00130-P-1869A)
    Title and negative number taken from caption on print. This image is not listed on currently known studio list. Unmounted print. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1869A
  - Darjeeling; General View from Observatory Hill, Looking South, circa 1880; 7 1/2 x 12 5/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-1871)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 16. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of this series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the dates after 1874 to 1879 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell," the Selim Tea Estate, and the Darjeeling Railway.
    Original negative number: 1871
  - View from Observatory Hill. Darjeeling, circa 1865; 8 7/8 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 25, Print RL-00130-P-1871A)
    Original negative number: 1871A
    Title and negative number, showing in white, are written on the negative, indicative of a later printing by the studio, after 1870. May be the work of Colin Murray rather than Bourne, and at a later date (after 1874).
  - Darjeeling; The Bandstand and Mall with Observatory Hill, circa 1880; 8 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 20, Print RL-00130-P-1874)
    Title lettered on print: Bandstand. Darjeeling. 1875. Studio lists this negative title as 1874 rather than 1875. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1874
  - Darjeeling; Observatory Hill, circa 1880; 8 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 20, Print RL-00130-P-1874A)
    Title and negative number taken from caption on print. This image is not listed on currently known studio list. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1874A
  - Darjeeling; Cane Bridge over the Teesta River Leading into Bhootan, circa 1880; 7 1/2 x 12 1/2 inches (Box 9, Print RL-00130-P-1876)
    Original negative number: 1876
    Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
  - Darjeeling; Cane Bridge over the Runjeet River below Darjeeling, circa 1880; 8 7/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-1879)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 3. On very large mount, 12 x 16 inches. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1879
  - Darjeeling; Bridge over the Rungnoo near its junction with the Runjeet, circa 1880; 9 1/4 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-1880)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 5. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1880
  - Darjeeling; View from Lebong Looking Towards the Snowy Range, circa 1880; 9 1/2 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 9, Print RL-00130-P-1888)
    On very large mount, 11 3/4 x 14 1/2 inches. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1888
  - Darjeeling; Group of Tree Ferns at Lebong, circa 1880; 9 1/2 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-1889)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 1. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1889
  - Darjeeling; Group of Tree Ferns in the Forest, circa 1869-1870; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 26, Print RL-00130-P-1894)
    Original negative number: 1894
    Signature is illegible. Mounted on board.
  - Darjeeling; A Pleasant Walk Near Tukvar, circa 1880; 9 1/8 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-1897)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 2. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1897
  - The Snows from Sandakfoo. Darjeeling, circa 1865; 7 1/2 x 11 5/8 inches (Box 24, Print RL-00130-P-1898)
    Original negative number: 1898
    Title and negative number, showing in white, are written on the negative, indicative of a later printing by the studio, after 1870. May be the work of Colin Murray rather than Bourne, and at a later date (after 1874). Title from reconstructed studio list for negative 1898 is "Darjeeling; A Picturesque 'Bit' on the Tukvar road." Mounted on heavy black paper.
  - Darjeeling; Forest Scene near Tukvar, circa 1880; 9 3/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 9, Print RL-00130-P-1899)
    On very large mount, 12 x 16 inches. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1899
  - Darjeeling; Picturesque Bridge over the Rungnoo below Ging, circa 1880; 9 1/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-1900)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 4. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1900
  - Darjeeling; View from below Ada Villa, circa 1880; 8 3/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 20, Print RL-00130-P-1903)
    Unmounted print. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1903
  - Darjeeling; Group of Bhooteas, circa 1880; 9 1/8 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-1904)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 51. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1904
  - Darjeeling; Group of Bhooteas, circa 1880; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-1905)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 50. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1905
  - Darjeeling; Lepcha man, circa 1880; 11 1/4 x 9 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-1907)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 57. Darjeeling; Lepcha man of Sikkim. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1907
  - Darjeeling; Lepcha woman, circa 1880; 10 7/8 x 8 3/4 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-1908)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 56. Darjeeling; Lepcha woman of Sikkim. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879-1881). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1908
  - Darjeeling: General View from Observatory Hill, circa 1880; 8 5/8 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 20, Print RL-00130-P-1911)
    On print, title given as "Snowy Range From Sandakfoo. Darjeeling." Corner of mount damaged. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1911
  - Darjeeling; General View from the Grounds of C. Barnes, Esq., circa 1880; 8 3/4 x 11 inches (Box 20, Print RL-00130-P-1912)
    Original negative number: 1912
    This estate is probably the tea garden established by Christine Barnes in 1871. Other landmarks and people's names mentioned in this series of images from Darjeeling suggest a date around 1880.
  - Darjeeling; From Jellapahar Road, circa 1865; 8 1/8 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 24, Print RL-00130-P-1914)
    Original negative number: 1914
    Title and negative number, showing in white, are written on the negative, indicative of a later printing by the studio, after 1870. May be the work of Colin Murray rather than Bourne, and at a later date (after 1874). Alternate title from reconstructed studio list for negative 1914 is "Darjeeling; View from the grounds of 'Beechwood Park.'" Mounted on board.
  - Darjeeling; From Jellapahar Road, circa 1865; 8 1/8 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 24, Print RL-00130-P-1916)
    Original negative number: 1916
    Title and negative number, showing in white, are written on the negative, indicative of a later printing by the studio, after 1870. May be the work of Colin Murray rather than Bourne, and at a later date (after 1874). Alternate title from reconstructed studio list for negative #1916 is "Darjeeling Hill from Lebong." Mounted on board.
  - Darjeeling; View of the Selim Tea Estate, showing the lower or Terai portion of the Estate, circa 1880; 7 1/2 x 12 inches (Box 20, Print RL-00130-P-1925)
    Unmounted print. The Selim Tea Estate was established around 1870. Other landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1925
  - The Sanitarium. Darjeeling, circa 1880; 9 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 20, Print RL-00130-P-1927A)
    Title and negative number taken from caption on print. This image is not listed on currently known studio list. Unmounted print. Various landmarks and people's names mentioned in the titles of the series of images taken in Darjeeling suggest the date circa 1880 (negative numbers 1869-1927). This includes the "late Dr. Campbell" (d. 1874), the Selim Tea Estate (est. 1871), and the Darjeeling Railway (built 1879-1881). These images are probably by Colin Murray or Charles Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 1927A
  - View from Eden Sanitarium. Darjeeling, circa 1880; 8 3/4 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 17, Print RL-00130-P-1927B)
    Original negative number: 1927B
  - Ajunta; Interior of Cave No. 9, 1869-1870; 9 1/4 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-1930)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 14. Print and album page bear no numbers; has been identified from captioned prints in other collections as image 1930.
    Original negative number: 1930
  - Cave Temple at Ajunta; Exterior, 1869-1870; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-1933)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 13. Number appears at top left of album page, partially cropped out.
    Original negative number: 1933
  - Ajunta; View of the Verandah of Cave No. 1, looking North, 1869-1870; 9 1/4 x 11 inches (Box 9, Print RL-00130-P-1936)
    Original negative number: 1936
  - Elora; Interior of the Indur Subha, with figure of Indrani, 1869-1870; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-1942)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 12. Print caption reads "Cave Temple; Interior." Number partially visible at top left of album page.
    Original negative number: 1942
  - Elora; Exterior of the Jugnath Subha (or Court of the Juggernauth), 1869-1870; 9 3/8 x 11 5/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-1943)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 11. Print caption reads "Cave Temple." Number partially visible at top left of album page.
    Original negative number: 1943
  - Ellora; Group of Mahadeo and Purwuty in the Dhumar Leva, 1870s-1880s; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 26, Print RL-00130-P-1945)
    Original negative number: 1945
    Unsigned, unnumbered. Caption on board mount is in French and has been translated into Bourne & Shepherd English title. Image is of temple sculptures.
  - Ootacamund; Panoramic View From a Spur of Dodabet, part 1, 1869-1870; 7 3/8 x 12 1/2 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1954)
    Unmounted print. Ootacamund is now officially known as Udagamandalam, in the state of Tamil Nadu.
    Original negative number: 1954
  - Ootacamund; East end of Ootacamund from Elk Hill, 1869-1870; 7 3/8 x 12 1/4 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1956)
    Original negative number: 1956
  - Ootacamund; East end of Ootacamund from Elk Hill Lodge, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 5/8 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1957)
    Original negative number: 1957
  - Ootacamund; General View from Elk Hill, 1869-1870; 7 3/8 x 12 1/4 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1958)
    Original negative number: 1958
  - Ootacamund; General View from Church Hill, looking South-West, 1869-1870; 7 3/8 x 12 1/4 inches (Box 20, Print RL-00130-P-1960)
    In larger mount than usual: 11 3/4 x 16 1/2 inches.
    Original negative number: 1960
  - Ootacamund; General View from Club Hill South-West, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 5/8 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1961)
    Original negative number: 1961
  - Ootacamund; General View looking East from above Sylk's Hotel, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 1/2 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1964)
    Original negative number: 1964
  - Ootacamund; General View from near Sheddon Hall, looking towards Elk Hill, slightly different, 1869-1870; 7 3/8 x 12 1/8 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1969)
    Original negative number: 1969
  - Ootacamund; General View from near Sheddon Hall, looking towards Dodabet, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 1/4 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1970)
    Original negative number: 1970
  - Ootacamund; General View from Hill above Bellevue, looking South, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 1/8 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1971)
    Original negative number: 1971
  - Ootacamund; The Lake and Downs from Elk Hill, Stormy Weather, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 7/8 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1976)
    Original negative number: 1976
  - Ootacamund; View Across the Lake from New Church, 1869-1870; 7 5/8 x 12 1/4 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1982)
    Original negative number: 1982
  - Ootacamund; View Across the Lower Lake, showing Baikie, etc, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 1/2 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1983)
    Original negative number: 1983
  - Ootacamund; View From Above Bombay House, looking towards Church and Club, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 1/2 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1984)
    Original negative number: 1984
  - Ootacamund; View From Stonehouse, looking towards the Bank, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 1/2 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1985)
    Original negative number: 1985
  - Ootacamund; View From "Lambsknowe" showing Stonehouse, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1986)
    Alternate title written in ink on mat, "Ootacamund, Neilgherries."
    Original negative number: 1986
  - Ootacamund; The Botanical Gardens from near "Lambsknowe", 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 1/2 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1987)
    Original negative number: 1987
  - Ootacamund; View from the Botanical gardens, fine Study of Trees, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 3/8 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1993)
    Original negative number: 1993
  - Ootacamund; The Botanical Gardens, Australian Trees in foreground, 1869-1870; 7 1/2 x 12 1/8 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-1995)
    Original negative number: 1995
  - Ootacamund; View From the Grounds of Stonehouse, small Lake in foreground, 1869-1870; 9 1/8 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-2001)
    Original negative number: 2001
  - Ootacamund; The Band-stand, and Ornamental Water in the Botanical Gardens, 1869-1870; 9 3/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 10, Print RL-00130-P-2003)
    Original negative number: 2003
  - Ootacamund; View from the Gardens above the Band-stand, 1869-1870; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 11, Print RL-00130-P-2004)
    Original negative number: 2004
  - Ootacamund; Mountain Gorge and Sholas (Wooded ravines) near Avalanche, 1869-1870; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 11, Print RL-00130-P-2006)
    Unmounted print. Number and caption written on back of print.
    Original negative number: 2006
  - The Neilgherries; Waterfall at Peermund, Lower Fall, 1869-1870; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 20, Print RL-00130-P-2009)
    Original negative number: 2009
  - The Neilgherries; Waterfall on the River Below the Croormund Bungalow, 1869-1870; 9 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 11, Print RL-00130-P-2018)
    Original negative number: 2018
  - The Neilgherries; Toda Mund, Village and Todas, 1869-1870; 9 1/4 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-2020)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 52.
    Original negative number: 2020
  - The Neilgherries; The Avalanche Valley from near the Bungalow, looking up, 1869-1870; 7 5/8 x 12 3/8 inches (Box 11, Print RL-00130-P-2021)
    Original negative number: 2021
  - The Neilgherries; View from Avalanche, looking East, 1869-1870; 7 1/4 x 12 1/8 inches (Box 11, Print RL-00130-P-2023)
    Caption on mount reads "Ootacamund."
    Original negative number: 2023
  - The Neilgherries; Rapids on the Pykara, above the Falls, 1869-1870; 7 5/8 x 12 5/8 inches (Box 11, Print RL-00130-P-2037)
    Mistakenly listed on original studio negative list as 2038. Caption on mount reads, "Another View Above the Falls."
    Original negative number: 2037
  - Tanjore; The Great Pagoda and Stone Bull from near the Entrance to the quadrangle, 1869-1870; 10 3/4 x 8 1/4 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-2045)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 34. Print title verified from numbered prints in other collections.
    Original negative number: 2045
  - Tanjore; Carved Stone Temple near the Pagodas, 1869-1870; 8 7/8 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 11, Print RL-00130-P-2049)
    Original negative number: 2049
  - The Rock of Trichinopoly from the East, circa 1869; 7 3/8 x 12 inches (Box 26, Print RL-00130-P-2054)
    Original negative number: 2054
  - Trichinopoly; General View of the Seringham Pagodas from the top of the Gateway, circa 1869; 9 1/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-2060)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 38. Title on album mount suggests number may be 2060.
    Original negative number: 2060
  - Three Small Goparums. Trichinopoly, circa 1869; 7 3/8 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 24, Print RL-00130-P-2062)
    Original negative number: 2062
    Taken at Tiruchirapalli, India. Title from reconstructed studio list reads "Trichinopoly; Three smaller Goparums from the top of the Thousand-Pillared hall." Unmounted.
  - Ceylon; Ouvah Country, Trees covered with creepers in the Pasara valley, circa 1870; 9 1/8 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 26, Print RL-00130-P-2168)
    Original negative number: 2168
    Negative number on print is scratched out; negative number assigned by dealer from unknown source. Title is from reconstructed studio catalog. Mounted on board.
  - Bombay; Bora Bazaar Street, 1870s-1880s; 7 5/8 x 12 3/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-2179)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 5. Number partially visible at top of album page. Bourne historian Rayner gives probable attribution to Colin Murray for this and some other Bombay images.
    Original negative number: 2179
  - Bombay; General view of the Great Cave of Elephanta, from the Entrance, 1870s-1880s; 9 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-2190)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 9. Number appears at top right of album page.
    Original negative number: 2190
  - Bombay; General View of the Great Cave of Elephanta from the Entrance, circa 1870; 8 7/8 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 24, Print RL-00130-P-2190)
    Title taken from reconstructed studio catalog. May have been taken by Bourne shortly before leaving for England. May also be later Bourne & Shepherd work. Unmounted.
  - Elephanta Cave; Head representing Brahma, Vishnu and Siva, 1870s-1880s; 9 3/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-2194)